[Music]
and we are live
good evening good day everybody it's
great to be back after a two day break
welcome to episode six week two of ask
abhijit
we have a very interesting week lined up
very interesting uh
discussions and today's discussion is
also very interesting
so before we get into it uh just a quick
announcement
i have started a new youtube channel
it's a clips channel
it's called a widget eclipse so i'm
uploading these individual questions on
this channel so
instead of going through an entire
episode you could browse through that
channel and
look at individual answers to questions
that you all have asked
so i have just started this channel i'm
going to keep uploading more and more
over there
so i would invite you and welcome you to
take a look
at that channel right so we have
a very interesting session ahead of us
today
artificial intelligence quantum
community computing
the future of humanity and all that and
you have asked
really really interesting questions a
whole bunch of questions
i obviously don't have the time to
answer them
all in these in these 90 minutes but i
have chosen a bunch of questions that
will
hopefully address the entire spectrum of
issues and topics and questions
that you all have raised so let us get
into it right away with question number
one
so this is by divisha please tell us
what
actually the artificial intelligence is
how does it work
can we develop it within us if yes then
how what are the three laws of robotics
and how will it affect our future
let's say a whole lot that's a number of
questions within one question but it's a
good
way to start this particular session so
what
is artificial intelligence artificial
intelligence is
a branch of computer science
it it seeks to create
uh machines that are intelligent enough
to be able to perform tasks that
usually would require human intelligence
right so examples of this is uh
self-driving cars so typically to drive
a car you need a human level of
intelligence
to deal with the situations and
eventualities in real time
so you need a lot of training and
practice to get all the
mental patterns ingrained in our in our
brain
and then we need to execute this in real
time as various things happen while
we're driving
so it requires a human level of
intelligence now today we are
increasingly seeing
sophisticated ever more sophisticated
self-driving systems uh the most famous
one is obviously tesla
so this is an example of artificial
intelligence it's a
set of computer programs algorithms it
says self learning system
that has reached the level of which
which at which it can
almost replace a human driver so as of
now tesla's cars require you to
be present to be awake and keep your
hands near the wheel
but it essentially drives itself but it
is iteratively getting better
so soon enough it will be able to drive
autonomously without human
uh assistance or supervision
so that's one example another example of
artificial intelligence
is uh surgery so
we are now getting to see robotics and
artificial intelligence
machines getting involved in minor and
basic and routine
surgeries for example you have this
lasik surgery that
corrects the the vision of people's eyes
so we are increasingly seeing this being
automated
and being done by a robotic machine
so that's an example of artificial
intelligence
a machine translation is another example
of artificial intelligence
the conversion of voice into text is
done nowadays autonomously
automatically in youtube itself you can
see this right
so when you replay a video when you have
a video which has already been uploaded
the youtube algorithm the artificial
intelligence behind it
or automatically translates the voice
into text now as of now it is not
entirely accurate
especially when it comes to non-english
pronunciations
and accents but it's getting better as
we speak
so these are examples of artificial
intelligence
these are computer systems that
essentially are taking over tasks
and the functions that require human
intelligence and this
is something that is rather new would
say paradigm
shift so until now we have had computer
systems that were
essentially dumb in nature garbage in
garbage out
you would program the computer you would
create softwares bundles of programs and
algorithms
with routines and subroutines so those
software packages could
handle a predetermined set of conditions
but now we are finding more and more
systems that
learn autonomously in an unsupervised
manner
that deal with all kinds of
eventualities as they as they learn
so that is in brief what artificial
intelligence is
what are the three laws of robotics well
that's something that uh the science
fiction writer
and scientist isaac asimov came up with
in the 1950s onwards
so that there is a bunch of laws now
instead of repeating them from memory
let me just
share that on the screen so
let me do that so
these are the three laws of robotics
these are essentially
these are not laws of physics or laws of
nature these are like
directives or guidelines for an
artificially intelligent robot
to follow so the first law says that a
robot may not
injure a human being or through inaction
allow
a human being to come to harm law number
two says that a robot
may must obey orders given it by human
beings
except where such orders would conflict
with the first law
and the third law is a robot must
protect its own existence
as long as such protection does not
conflict with this first
or second law and there's a fourth law
as well that
isaac assimo introduced later it's
actually called the zeroth law
it says that a robot may not harm
humanity
also in action cause humanity to come to
harm
so these are the three or four laws of
robotics
these are guidelines these are directive
principles these are not actual
laws so these are not hard coded into
every artificial intelligence these are
not hard-coded
into every robot with artificial
intelligence this is something
that isaac asimov and people who deal
with the ethics and philosophy of
ai they would like laws such as these to
be implemented
and to be followed by all ai systems
right
so this essentially ensures that
human supremacy is maintained over ai
systems over computer systems
is it possible is it is it always going
to be the
the way it was envisaged as
well not necessarily and
it is possible for for a corporation or
government to
develop an artificial intelligence
system
that doesn't uh that contravenes these
three laws of robotics so that's
entirely
voluntary it is not guaranteed that it's
going to be
it's going to be implemented so that's
what the three laws of robotics
are how will it affect our future how
will ai affect our future
well ai is the future uh it is
it is going to upend the world it's
turning everything around
it's it's already its effects are
already being seen
the the ubiquitous presence of ai
algorithms everywhere we have our mobile
phones with us we are on the internet
ai is tracking our every movement
it's following our footsteps it knows
where we are it knows our patterns
it knows what we like what we dislike
what we click on what we don't click on
and so much more it essentially knows
more about our psychology
and our likes and dislikes and desires
and wants
and relationships and whatnot it knows
all of this better than
it understands us essentially better
than we even understand ourselves
because it goes into the deep
subconscious
so this is the future and right now who
is benefiting from ai that is the real
question that we will go into
in subsequent questions right so this is
a great way to start it's a good
question
let's go to question two
this is by harika explain about
quantum computing so this is a closely
allied
technology ai and quantum computing are
increasingly going hand in hand
they are not the same thing but quantum
computing is going to make ai more
powerful
so what is quantum computing right in
very brief quantum computing is the
application of the laws of quantum
mechanics
in producing more powerful computers now
that's a very vague thing you want to
understand a thing about it
so let me explain in more detail
so the computers that we use today
whether it's cell phones or tablets or
laptops
these are called classical computers
these computers are essentially
enormous and enormously powerful
calculators
they do all their processing in terms of
ones and
zeros right so all the processing is
either ones or zeros zeros
yes or no and that's how the logic flows
and
typically a processor would perform
millions of
such individual one or zero computations
per second
and that's how we get uh computing power
right
so all data all images all text
all speech at the fundamental level is
represented in terms of ones and zeroes
and these binary operations are what
drives
a computer so the integrated of circuit
which is at the heart of computers it is
composed of
transistors or mosfets m-o-s-f-e-t
metal oxide semiconductor field effect
transistor
so these are the units that store ones
and zeros and store data and
perform the basic yes or no computations
right so these deal in terms of
bits bits of information a bit is either
a zero
or a one it can either be a zero or a
one
right so a transistor would generally do
these logic calculations
based on these bits so a bit in a
classical computer is either zero or one
in a quantum computer you have the laws
of quantum mechanics
because today we have miniaturized these
transistors that perform these
operations and store
data we have many miniaturize them to
the level that they are now
as small as molecules and almost at the
atomic level
and it is at this level this ultra
microscopic level
that the laws of quantum mechanics come
into effect
and these laws are unlike anything we
see and
experience in the day-to-day mundane
world
so in quantum computers we have
something called
quantum bits qubits so a classical bit
is one or zero
a quantum bit can be in a superposition
so it's either one
or zero or one and zero
so it has three possible values right
it's a superposition
of three three different values now
that's just a little bit more than one
and zero it can contain one zero or one
and zero
but when you place these different bits
when you take a whole number
large bunch of bits and you place them
in a quantum superposition
that's when you can create inside a
quantum computer an
immense multi-dimensional computing
space that can
crunch through and annihilate extremely
complex problems in a very short period
of time
so for example this is at least a
thousand times
minimum faster than a classical computer
so you would you can have quantum
computers to deal
almost today that can perform in one
second
a calculation that would take the
fastest super computer
a week to go to perform so that's the
paradigm shift that we are
eventually going to have so there is the
concept of quantum supremacy
to produce a to to create a quantum
computer
that can outperform the best classical
supercomputer
in a certain calculation and google has
claimed quantum supremacy
and a chinese university has also
claimed that it has achieved
quantum supremacy so quantum computing
is about
leveraging the and exploiting the laws
of quantum mechanics
coherent superpositions quantum
entanglement
uh quantum tunneling and such like so
these are the
laws of quantum mechanics that are
exploited in quantum computers
and that's what gives us this enormous
massive
power computing power compared to a
classical computer
now the thing is that it is important
right now
for quantum computing to take off
because it has been estimated
that by the year 2040 we will no longer
be able to produce
sufficient power to run all the
computers
that will be that will be present in the
world by 2040.
we're going to run out of compute run
out of electrical power we will no
longer be
able to generate that much electrical
power that these devices require
because computing is is exploding
computers are
everywhere you have things like bitcoin
mining and
and cryptocurrency mining which which
are extremely
energy intensive so very soon in just a
couple of decades it is distributed we
will run out of
power to to generate to to to run all
these computers
so if you have quantum computers there
are a thousand times
more powerful and a thousand times
faster than classical computers or even
more
then that could essentially alleviate
this impending power crisis so that's
why
industry is uh rushing to
develop ever more powerful quantum
computers we are in the infancy of this
particular technology because coherent
quantum superpositions are extremely
fragile
they need ultra cold temperatures so
that takes a lot of technical know-how
so this technology is still being
developed
a quantum computer that is as powerful
that is a thousand times as powerful as
a classical superconduct
uh super computer is typically just the
size of a refrigerator
so that's the kind of technology that is
beginning to
emerge it's in its infancy but it's
going to
uh go forward so that is the real big
deal right now
that is what corporations and
governments are pursuing
so every corporation and every
government that has ambitions of leading
the world
is taking this extremely seriously and
there are
all kinds of experiments being done
right now to develop
this technology so that is in brief
quantum computing let's go to the next
question
okay this is by men god how
how does an ai make decisions does it
give
only pre-programmed answers or can it
also create new answers and decisions
which are not programmed
that's a good question that lies at the
heart
of artificial intelligence so typically
our pro computers are programmed we have
software packages
that run in a particular manner right
that's what
your typical regular programs and
computers are like
now artificial intelligence has an
entirely different
way of operating it has something called
unsupervised learning
so it it which is a branch of machine
learning
so in machine learning what happens is
that a computer system
learns autonomously without supervision
it learns on the basis of statistics and
data and trial and error
and we have seen this i mean this is now
almost uh
a routine thing right so you have
computers that
learn how to play chess from scratch by
just playing chess games against itself
hundreds of thousands or millions of
times and it eventually is able to reach
a stage where
it can defeat the best grandmaster on
the planet this happened more than 20
years ago 20 years ago
when a computer called deep blue
defeated gary kasparov
so this is automated self-directed
unsupervised learning based on data
based on statistics based on
patterns that it detects and based on
trial and error
so these computer systems are
unsupervised they are not
programmed they programmed themselves
essentially
so right now these uh
deep learning networks neural networks
we don't even know how they come
how they arrive at certain solutions and
we don't even know exactly how they
learn
because this happens on its own in a
very very
quick manner it happens very fast so you
cannot see every computation
and every calculation it is doing inside
its memory so this is the thing right
now
that we even in the infancy of ai
we are not able to really pinpoint how
exactly it came to certain solutions
right and these systems are right now
quite i mean they are already quite
strong but it's only
going to improve in the future so that's
the thing
so the answer to your question is simple
these are not
pre-programmed systems they program
themselves they learn
on their own based on the data that is
made available to them
so that is the deal about ai
good question let's go to the next one
is by lena what will happen when ai
achieves
consciousness would it break the three
laws of robotics what are your views
about ai being an existing
existential threat for humans
okay we don't know what's going to
happen when ai achieves consciousness
uh all possibilities are open
will ai achieve consciousness is the big
question
consciousness is something that seems to
be present only in
biological systems so we have these
biological computers that we call brains
we have these all other species of
animals on our planet
have brains of various kinds of various
levels of complexity
and we are we know that there is
consciousness
in animals you have a dog that dog is
conscious he has
he or she has emotions has memory has
intelligence a cat has consciousness
monkeys and apes of consciousness
i believe that there are levels of
consciousness and
almost every living being that we know
it does exhibit
some form of consciousness so this is a
property of biological systems from what
we know thus far we have never
encountered an artificial system that
has
what we call consciousness the thing is
we don't even have
a scientific definition of what
consciousness is
what would it take for an artificial
intelligent
system artificially intelligent system
to achieve this
so consciousness seems to arise from the
structure of the neurons of the brain
that's one school of thought that it is
an emergent phenomenon
it arises it emerges out of the
incredible complexity
and the depth of connections trillions
of connections
or neural connections that are present
in the brain so scientists are trying to
emulate that by creating artificial
neural networks that mimic
what we have in the brain the path the
the architecture
of the brain and what we find is that
these neural network exhibits
exhibit behaviors that are similar to
what the human brain exhibits for
example they need sleep
after a certain period of computation
they need to have a period of inactivity
otherwise they start producing garbage
data garbage information
their computations go alright so
artificial neural networks seem to
exhibit similar patterns
as the human brain at a very very small
level
so if these networks were allowed were
to be allowed
to become large maybe on the scale of a
mammalian brain
or a human brain then maybe they would
develop some form of
consciousness now even if it were to
develop consciousness will it become
intelligent enough
to learn everything about the world that
takes time
so when a human being is born we
human beings we have the our brains are
the most
complex uh computers
so to say in the known universe that we
know of
right these are the most powerful and
most complex computing
machines these are biological computers
when a human being is born when a baby
is born
it has that machine but it's a blank
slate
and it takes the baby at least a year at
least 10 months to a year
to start forming the first words because
it has to
absorb a great deal of auditory sound
information
and start generating patterns and start
associating those patterns of sounds
with certain objects
and then later on with certain feelings
and emotions and colors so it takes a
great deal of time for this incredibly
powerful computer
to start making sense of the world and
even at the
the age of 10 or 12 or 15 a human being
is typically extremely immature
immature means it does not it may have a
lot of wisdom
it may have a lot of data and
information and knowledge but it doesn't
have
wisdom which comes from pattern
recognition so
it takes a great deal of time
a neural network like the brain to
achieve maturity
and be able to make a difference in the
world so i would say that even if
a an ai were to achieve consciousness it
would take
it some to understand the world
and that to only if it is allowed
sensory information from outside
if it is kept within within certain
limits
it would be like a human being kept
inside a chair inside a cage
without access to outside information so
so that's what would happen
when if an air were to achieve
consciousness it can still be controlled
right if it is uncontrolled if it gets
access to all the resources of the world
will it break the three laws of robotics
well it depends on on the aia it may
well do it
there is no guarantee it won't break
these laws of robotics
so if so to answer your last question
what are my views about
it being an existential threat it can
become an existing existential threat
for humans
if it is allowed to grow unimpeded and
if it is
allowed access to the world's resources
unimpeded access to the world's
resources and to decision making
powers so yes that is definitely
a possibility next question
this is by rahul uh do you think one
would be able to preserve
one's consciousness in the future can we
outlive our physical bodies
what's the point to life if there's
nothing of death
it may be hard to answer this as it
falls in the philosophical realm but my
personal
take yes this is
a philosophical question to uh to to a
certain extent
about what's the point to life if there
is nothing after death
but to answer the first part of the
question
can is it will it be possible to
preserve one's consciousness
in the future so that is currently the
stuff of science fiction that you can
upload your brain and your memories
to a computer now the thing is that
our brain is structured in a very
specific manner it has a certain
architecture that and it has
evolved over millions of years it has
layers it has a primitive
reptilian brave brain and there are more
layers to it and the
outer layer is what we call the
prefrontal cortex and all
that is believed to be the seat of our
humanity right
so it has a very specific architecture
and
in order to upload one's consciousness
to and
to a computer system i believe it would
be necessary for that computer system to
also have
a similar architecture internal
architecture otherwise
certain connections and the certain data
may not be replicated properly certain
connections may be lost certain memories
may be lost or they would be imperfect
and
the essence of what we call humanity may
be lost in that
it may just end up as a as a collection
of data
with certain connections but the the
spark that
makes us human this the consciousness
may not be present
and even if one were to upload one's
consciousness into a machine
you're not uploading it we're creating a
copy
of our consciousness so it's a separate
consciousness
that when we upload it is the same as
ours but
as it becomes conscious and functional
it will become separate from us it will
immediately be separate from us it will
go in its own direction
so it will be like having two of myself
but two separate individuals right and
they will have their own future paths
and they will have their own separate
experiences if they are allowed to
so to upload one's consciousness even if
that is feasible
doesn't mean that your pers your
consciousness will persist beyond
the physical death of the body a copy of
your consciousness will
persist in a physical
data system a computer system of sorts
right
so even if it is if even if it becomes
possible to
make a copy of one's consciousness it
will just be a copy
after once once a person dies their
consciousness
from which a copy was made that original
will well if if
that's what it happens then that
consciousness will cease to exist
unless there is what the philosophers
and
various religious systems believe that
consciousness persists beyond death
of which we have no scientific evidence
right
so even if this technology becomes
available it's not going to extend your
consciousness beyond the point of
physical death
so that's the answer
okay next question
yes what's my take on crispr
if this is going to be the future what
are the chances of an
intelligence divide among future kids
will a normal kid stand any chance
against these genetically modified
super kids so crispr
is a gene editing technology i think
it's called crispr cas9
so it's a technology that allows
us that allows scientists or the users
to add or replace to add or delete genes
in vivo in in in a living being
and it also allows the
if if you do it the right way to make
these changes
inheritable so not only can you change
the genome of a living
person but you can actually make that
change be
inheritable in the person's children
so that is in very brief in a nutshell
what crispr is
and this is a technology that raises a
great deal of
ethical and philosophical and other
concerns
right and legal questions and much more
so because of this technology it is
possible
to choose the hair color the eye color
the the height and much more of children
so you can basically create these super
kids
or designer babies right so in the
future the rich and the powerful
and the ones who can afford to access
this technology
may be possibly able to do this
so they may be able to have very
specific kinds of children right
and these changes may be inheritable in
their children's children
so if this sort of thing becomes the
norm
then there will definitely be an
intelligence divide among the haves and
the have nots
the ones who have been enhanced using
crispr and those who cannot afford to do
that
so yeah you could essentially create a
race of super humans
with greatly enhanced abilities greatly
enhanced
physiques uh superior heart
heart function superior intelligence and
and much more so a normal child would
eventually as the technology
advances a normal child would not stand
a chance against these genetically
modified super kids so that's a very
good question
the this raises a lot of ethical issues
is it
ethically is it ethically fine
to to do such things i mean aren't we
supposed to let
uh the laws of genetics
and the laws of nature take their own
course
or are we going to start modifying
ourselves and
the thing is we don't even understand
what happens
the longer and the longer it effects the
long-term
effects of such genetic modifications
because uh
our genome okay let's take our genome
for example it's the entire contents of
our dna
our dna is divided into 23 chromosomes
and all these chromosomes they make up
the human genome
now we understand about two or three
percent of the human genome
and about more than 95 is absolutely not
understood at all
it's called the dark matter of dna
because it seems to be
non-coding dna it doesn't seem to have
any purpose but it's there
in our genome and it's it's passed on
from generation to generation
and we don't know what these genes do
what this dark matter of the dna does
but just because we don't understand
what it
what it does doesn't mean that it
doesn't do anything
it may be doing something it may have
some functions that have
that have evolved over over millions of
years
and it may have some real uh function in
regulating and
our bodies so if one were to make
certain changes in the dna
it may have some effects because of the
other part of the dna
the majority of the dna that we do not
understand
and this may have effects that may
become visible several generations down
the line
at which stage it may be too late to
rectify the mistakes that were done
so these are technologies that are in
their infancy they have not matured by
any means
and i think it is extremely dangerous
and unethical to start experimenting on
humans as if we know everything
right we we are in the infancy of this
technology
and some chinese scientists have already
created
crispr edited babies and
the experiment failed i don't think it
caused any harm in those two babies two
twin girls
but we don't know yet time will tell how
how their life goes
so the chinese don't seem to really um
worry too much about ethics and all that
they are concerned more with world
domination
and they have they have a lot of people
so it's okay to
mess up a few lives i expect so that's
the thing with crispr it's a very
powerful technology but the kind of
power it gives you
it it can be easily misused and the
mistakes that
are made with this power they are almost
impossible to rectify and we don't even
understand
this technology fully or even slightly
so that is what crispr is it is
definitely
the future you're going to have gene
editing you're going to have gene drives
and much more it is the future it's in
the infancy
of the technology so it is a little
early to to start making a human
to start doing human experimentation but
in the future i think it's going to
create
a significant divide among people among
genetically enhanced people
and the people who cannot afford the
technology or do who don't have have
access to it
so these technologies artificial
intelligence quantum computing
gene editing these are tools
any technology is merely a tool a stick
is a tool a gun is a tool nuclear energy
nuclear power
is a tool the concepts of flight
right power flight that is a tool
everything is a tool
and a tool can be used for good or for
bad
a stick can be used for good alphabet
computers can be used for good or for
evil
nuclear power can change the world it
can power the entire planet
or it can destroy the planet and
similarly ai
quantum computing crispr gene editing
all of these if they can be used for
good they can
well solve all the problems of humanity
and if they are used
by a very small number of people to to
empower themselves and enrich themselves
then they can exacerbate
all the problems the world is currently
seeing for example
today we already have
the technology to solve world hunger and
many diseases
we have the the ability to to
basically give everybody a decent life
everybody on the planet
and yet that's not happening because
there's a great deal of inequality and
that inequality is
done on purpose so technology is just a
tool
it all depends on how it is used and it
cannot change human nature
so these problems are going to be well
they're gonna occur in the future
including crispr and its effects
so good question it's good that you
brought this up gene editing
next question
this is by sunny niggy what are my
thoughts on billionaires like bill gates
trying to aggressively
uh promote gmos and hybrid seeds in
nations in the controversy of facebook
selling information
to cambridge and analytica is there any
possibility that there will be
there will be a time when such powerful
people would control
major interests of nations good question
so what is a gmo a gmo is a genetically
modified
organism so once again this is about
gene editing
it's about artificially changing certain
genes
in let's say plants in seeds and
creating a new kind of
a new breed a new species of
plant for example there's something
called golden rice
so it's a new kind of rice that's been
genetically engineered and it supposedly
provides a great deal of vitamin d
so you don't need to go on the sun you
can just sit at home eat the
golden rice and you will get the vitamin
d that you need
so that is one example of a gmo then you
have these genetically modified
mosquitoes
that will breed with regular mosquitoes
and render render
or something like that so so there are
experiments in which such
genetically modified mosquitoes have
been released in the wild
and so that is what gmos is it's mostly
to do with food crops
modified food drops that will be more
tolerant to drought that we need less
water that would be more tolerant to
pests
and other uh funguses and those things
diseases
plant diseases so it is all about
solving
the food problems of the world so there
are some
some companies and organizations are
genetically modifying
food crops to uh
to increase the yields and all that
right now the question is once again the
same
do we understand the long-term effects
of
of modifying and editing genes if we
introduce a new kind of gene
inside an organism it has a great deal
of dna that we don't understand
and this dna interacts with each other
and we don't understand
what happens and what effects it has so
this g
and and the other thing is that we don't
know what ellipse they are doing in the
in the genes of this organism they may
be adding
or editing certain genes that we don't
know about right
for for certain purposes that we are not
aware of
so the question is can we trust these
people can we trust these organizations
and these this powerful
corporations and these so-called
philanthropists what are they actually
trying to achieve
what effect will it have on human beings
who consume these genetically modified
plants and seeds and hybrid
uh legumes and all that we don't know so
it is a big concern
firstly we don't know the long-term
effects of these gene
of these edits in the genes and secondly
we don't know if they are introducing
certain certain
things that we are not aware of for
certain uh agendas to serve certain
agendas
so that is a big problem and that's why
i personally
am against gmos we have
we have a great variety of food crops
and all kinds of seeds that have existed
for thousands of years
they have evolved over thousands of
years we have great varieties
of rice potatoes of wheat of
all kinds of other food food
crops so i would say that it is
dangerous to create genetically modified
organisms
because we know what happens when you
introduce new organisms in
an environment where that organism
doesn't belong you have these
uh invasive species
that destroy the local environment some
people have introduced certain species
of fish
in certain lakes and rivers from from
far away
and they have wreaked havoc on the local
ecosystem
and the same goes for invasive insect
species
invasive reptiles and snakes so
if you were to introduce new species
that you have created artificially
it's going to have effects that we don't
understand right now
so it's not a good idea in my opinion to
do this without
understanding fully what the long-term
effects are
so that's about gmos uh the controversy
of facebook selling information to
cambridge analytica
it's about big data see big data
facebook
google uh twitter
and the like they give us free services
right
we can access all these services for
free
the thing is this when the service is
you are the product you are the product
they are selling
so facebook runs ads the the customer
the user of facebook is the product
right so that's how facebook makes money
by selling the customers eyeballs and
and attention to advertisers the same
goes for google and youtube
and instagram and twitter and all that
so and it's not just that there's a
great deal of other data that is
collected metadata
that is in a way very intrusive
so when so this information is very
valuable data is the new oil
so that is what was this entire
controversy about
facebook selling information to
cambridge analytica without informing
users
and it has a great deal of applications
you can change governments you can
change the opinions of people by
selective targeting
right you can trend certain hashtags
trends certain news stories
which may be true or false and you can
influence people's opinions people's
moods and and much more
so you can so you can artificially
engineer entire societies entire
countries by by the means of
manipulating the data
and that's what big data is all about
now companies like facebook
google twitter etc they transcend the
national boundaries
right they come into your your country
your sovereign country
and then they tell you how to behave
they tell you the rules
they impose rules upon you which they
can arbitrarily change
they can block people they can ban
people they can prevent you from saying
certain things
they can prevent certain political
opinions from being aired
certain religious opinions from being
aired and they can
by doing all this control the entire
society
so that is one of the main issues of big
data
it it essentially is making national
sovereignty
increasingly obsolete and these big data
companies they now
be they are in some ways more powerful
than certain countries
and they are now trying to negotiate
as if they are a sovereign entity of
their own so this is the same model that
the east india companies
used to great with great success
they came into india as a corporation as
a company
they wanted to trade and as they gained
more power they
gained more land they started imposing
their foreign laws
on indians right and eventually they
took over the whole country
so this is the east india company
company model
which all of these big data companies
are are currently
using it's the same model it's used in a
different way
it's all virtual now it's all online
it's all about data
but the effects are essentially the same
and that's that's the that's the that's
why it's such a big
threat to the sovereignty of nations
so that's about uh cambridge analytica
is there any possibility there will be a
time when powerful people would control
major interest operations yes like i
just said
these powerful people these powerful
corporations are now becoming
effectively more powerful than many
nations
and yes eventually everything will be
privatized
even countries may be privatized without
the people knowing about it
especially if the politicians and the
so-called leaders of these countries
make
deals with these corporations in that
case the entire countries
will become privatized and you will all
become commodities so that is the great
danger
right now see the united states
we think of it as this great paradise
but it's a country
it's the most unequal country in the
world
in a sense because it's a very very
small fraction of
the country's population that controls
all the power
and the controls more than two-thirds of
the money in the united states
so it's a great place if you're rich
it's a terrible place if you're poor the
poor in that country they have to work
three jobs
18 hours a day just to put food
on the plates on the tables of the
family
and this inequality is is increasing
in the united states it's it's becoming
like an oligarchy
right so that is the model that is now
being used to
it's now being exported to other
countries and
the tentacles of power are spreading
worldwide because of artificial
intelligence because of big data
so that is the situation we are in right
now
the world is changing very fast the
2020s are going to be a decade of great
change of great geopolitical change of
great power shifts
uh china is pushing back it has closed
off its internet it doesn't allow google
or any american company in russia is
going is is
doing that to a certain extent and
russia and china
have clearly declared that they do not
believe in the western system of values
and
international law and all that they have
their own way of looking at things
so they are pushing back at this system
so it's a it's a very interesting time
it's a time of great change it's a time
of great peril for
for the ordinary people of the world so
let's see where it goes
so great question
this is by darshana what are my thoughts
about
neuralink if a chip is installed inside
of the human body
can it potentially rectify biological
disorders
wouldn't it be a threat to natural human
instinct
will the chip really enhance our
intelligence or make us mere
robots who function as per orders
so that's a great question i got a
couple of other questions about this
although the other question is will
neural link cause adverse effects and
one more
whom will neural link benefit the most
so let's start with that question whom
will neural link benefit
benefit the most it will benefit
those who own it it is owned by elon
musk
isn't it and consortium of other people
mainly elon musk
so these technologies
are created by private companies and
they are not created for the benefit of
humanity
they are created for the purpose of
enriching the company
enriching the owner and of increasing
and expanding the power
that's all there is to this
entrepreneurship is about
getting rich it's about acquiring
capital and acquiring power
and acquiring leverage and they do this
by creating new technologies that are
very useful
to people that are very enticing that
give you a lot of benefits
but and they try to hook you to these
technologies by giving you all these
free benefits
or paid benefits in case they're so
they're so beneficial
but eventually it's going to end up
benefiting the company
mostly it's usually it's like this
that's how it happens
that's the thing about big data it's
about that's how it works with facebook
and google
and twitter and all that and i think
with neural link again it will benefit
elon musk the most it will
definitely enrich him to a great deal it
will increase his power and leverage
and the question is also about are
will there be any adverse effects of
neural link
so let's let's go into what neural link
is neural link is a
chip that is installed surgically
inside one's skull and it interfaces
with the brain it is a brain machine
interface so the the core concept is
something like this when we are trying
to communicate
non-verbal information non-verbal data
then our bandwidth is very limited so
let's say i'm making a
voice call or a video call then i can
convey a great deal of information just
by speaking
but when i'm trying to communicate
non-verbal
non-visual information the bandwidth is
very limited because
the only thing i have is my fingers to
type
on the on the on the uh
type pad of a computer or on the
touchpad of a
of a smartphone or a tablet so that is a
very slow process it takes a great deal
of time to type
and to convey information especially
complex information
right so what if there was an interface
between the brain and the computer
that would directly allow you to
transmit great deals of
great amounts of data in a very short
period of time so it
entirely takes away the concept of
typing manually and doing all that
so it will speed up a great deal of
processes and all that
so that is the core concept and the
purpose of neural link
to give a working to create a working
brain machine
interface so you will be able to uh to
upload data
to transmit data mentally to a computer
system
you'll also be able to download data
from a computer system directly into the
brain
so that's what it is all about so it's a
chip that you install
inside your skull there's an outside
piece an inside piece
and then there is there is these uh
electrodes and the sensors that actually
penetrate your
brain tissue they go inside the brain so
you puncture your brain tissue
and then they go inside and that's how
it interfaces with the brain
so are there any adverse effects of this
so this is something we don't understand
at all it's a very very new technology
it's never been tried before we don't
know what happens when you inject
raw data into the brain the brain
has evolved over millions actually
billions of years
from the very early stages it is
designed to function
in a certain way right and
we don't understand how the brain works
at all we only have a very very crude
idea of the functioning of the brain
now if when we're to inject raw data
into the brain
that what what effect would it have are
we sure if it's going to reach the right
portions of the brain are we going to
start seeing the
dreams with our eyes with our eyes
closed can we see movies
with our eyes closed because of neural
link eventually that's the kind of thing
they want to achieve
but will it have adverse effects this
injection of raw data into the brain
will it cause
insanity because the brain can only uh
the brain can only handle a certain bit
rate
per second and i believe there have been
certain calculations of this of this bit
rate that the brain can process
cognitively
per second if you inject more bits more
data
then will it have will it overload the
brain will it impede the brain's
functioning will it
cause the percept to well go into a
certain state that is
not good for them we don't know as of
now
so there are many unanswered questions
right now the testing is being done on
non-human
brains so they have shown in
neural link they had shown that there
were pigs that were implanted with these
electro these with these devices and you
could see in real time what sort of
brain activity was going on
so it's in the very infancy eventually
they are going to
perfect the technology or at least
improve upon it
and i believe they will still soon start
testing on
human subjects so if it is done well it
may
uh improve the human condition and give
us
mental superpowers possibly we may be we
may be able to dream or watch movies
with our eyes closed
uh we may have designer dreams of or
escape into virtual vacations with our
eyes closed
this may be all paid services possibly
that's eventually the kind of thing that
may happen
if this technology matures and if it
does not harm the human brain
on the other hand it's possible that it
will render
people into zombies or digital slaves
so there are all kinds of possibilities
first of all this is a very new
technology injecting data
into the brain is an unproven thing we
don't know the consequences
secondly if the technology works it can
be used for good
or for a great deal of bad as well like
every technology
uh will it enhance our intelligence or
make us mere robots
it may enhance our intelligence we may
be able to access the internet just by
closing our eyes or mentally thinking
about it
so we may never have to memorize things
again
but but does that make us intelligent or
dumb that's the question isn't it
if we don't ever have to memorize
anything again does it make us more
intelligent or more stupid
these are questions that we haven't ever
addressed before so that's the
that's the threshold that we are
crossing right now
because of these new technologies so the
future
is is unknown we are going into the
future with our eyes open right now
and let's see how it goes so all these
technologies are being developed by
american corporations
if these technologies mature
and become widespread it's going to give
them a great deal
of power over the people of the world
and china is the competitor they are
also doing various experiments they also
i believe are doing some
brain computer interface tests
so we will soon find out about all this
so so the
the the future is uncertain we don't
know
whether neural link is going to be
beneficial or harmful
but we will soon find out when it is
unveiled and
it is implemented on human subjects
next question this is by bowen
what will be the role of ai in robotics
in terms of health care and early
diagnosis of diseases
in the future so this is a very good
application of ai this is
an application that will actually help
humanity
so we already find robots being used in
minor or routine surgeries and
as these systems get better just like
with self-driving cars
you will eventually see robotic machines
and artificial intelligences doing more
complex
surgeries so eventually this is going to
be more reliable than a human doctor
or a human surgeon so that's one good
thing come out of ai in robotics
early diagnosis of diseases yeah that's
another thing so
right now to diagnose diseases we look
at
test data we do a number of tests on a
person
and then we look at the data that we
find from this test and then we come at
some sort of conclusion
as to what ailment or illness or disease
that individual
is suffering from now ai could automate
this process
it could sift through vast amounts of
data and pinpoint
exactly in a very short period of time
what exactly this person
is actually suffering from so that is
another great uh
benefit that ai would have if it is
implemented
in this direction and yeah it will
happen but it will be commercialized
so these disease diagnostics and all
will be commercialized they will be
available not for everyone
but they'll be available for a certain
price
that's what's going to happen the other
interesting thing is that ai will be
able to
actually it will be able to create
new drugs so right now we have a number
of molecules
of antibiotics that are used for for
fighting various
bacterial infections and various
diseases now as
you must be aware many of these
bugs many of these bacteria are becoming
resistant
to antibiotics mainly because of overuse
of antibiotics by doctors they prescribe
antibiotics even for viral illnesses
like cuffs and colds so that's why
bacteria are becoming increasingly
uh immune to these antibiotics we are
having to start
to start using stronger and stronger
antibiotics
for example you have mdr tuberculosis
multiple drug resistant tuberculosis
even xdr tuberculosis
extensively drug-resistant tuberculosis
so
and this is happening in other diseases
as well you have mdr and xd of malaria
as well
so it is now imperative for us to start
discovering
new antibiotics to combat these
illnesses
which essentially means that we have to
discover new molecules
for these antibiotics now this is where
ai comes in
ai can shift through entire immense
amounts of data and databases of various
kinds of molecules and chemical
chemical substances and it can
iteratively
through trial and error look at what
what has worked in the past what doesn't
work in the past
and come up with potential solutions for
various
uh diseases and illnesses so ai may be
able to automate
the process of searching for viable
molecules for future antibiotics
so that's another application of ai so
there's a great deal of
good that ai can do but it is all
controlled by small corporations by
by a small number of people large
corporations and large governments
and the the aim is to commercialize all
these applications
so once again this is going to be used
to enrich
certain people and not benefit
humanity as a whole that is the real
issue
ai is is a very powerful technology it
can have
great benefits it can solve all our
problems
the problem is that the issue is that
it's going to be used only for
commercial purposes
and for governmental military purposes
and all that
it's not going to be used as as we see
right now
the direction the world is going in ai
is going to be used
for these specific agendas only either
commercially
or militarily to empower and enrich
either individuals or corporations or
governments so that is the real issue
right now that is the ethical dilemma
that we are facing
with ai it's a good question
next question
this is by c month suppose we develop an
ai based on dharma and used it in the
administration of our country
how will it impact and help revive our
civilization
will it be very difficult or easy for
our countrymen to assimilate
since we have forgotten our ethos due to
past centuries of
slavery okay this is a very good
question
an ai based on dharma so dharma is
essentially a set of rules
these are uh these are moral
principles it's a set of values
that can be programmatically implemented
in an artificial intelligence for sure
so there have been many uh
suggestions for for implementing ai in
legal systems for example replacing
judges and codes with just an ai so you
feed the data of a case into an ai
and it's going to tell you who's the
culprit who's the ability party who's
the
person who is innocent or what is the
legal outcome of a specific
case so ai can take this can make these
decisions decisions
very quickly and very effectively and
with a lesser
probability of error than a human judge
or a human legal system could do
so there have already been uh
suggestions to implement
ai in legal systems in laws
so one could definitely potentially
develop an ai and
implement it based on the precepts and
principles of dharma
and one could use that in the
administration of
a country our country so yeah if one
would do that it would definitely help
revive our civilization and it would
help us
govern and run the country in a much
better way
and in principle and in line with the
principles and precepts
and values of our age our civilization
that have existed for
thousands of years will this ever be
done
as of now it's not possible because we
first of all in india don't have ai
we are not doing anything any any
research and development in ai
and secondly our constitution and laws
are
not based on dharma they are dharmic
they are based on foreign values
on western values in western morality
so unless india somehow
changes its constitution and laws and
bases them on its own indigenous value
system
on dharma unless that happens you will
never see this ai's ai based
implemented implementation of dharma
ever so it is possible in principle
but at this stage we are in right now i
don't see it happening
anytime soon firstly because we don't
have the ai
capabilities in india we are not
pursuing it we are not
doing any research of any significance
and secondly we have
a very different system of governance in
india
but if one were to do it it would
definitely help us revive the
civilization for sure
next this is by mayank
will it ever be practically possible for
humans to go
to even our nearest star system proxima
centauri
within the reasonable lifetime of a
single human being even after cryogenic
sleep that's a good question and there's
a related question which asks whether
yeah it asks when will cryogenic sleep
become
a reality okay so let's deal with the
first question
first will it ever be practically
possible for
humans to go to proxima centauri
so the fastest spacecraft ever launched
is the parker
solar probe i believe it achieved the
speed of 0.06 percent the speed of light
so based on that speed
it would take about 6 000 or so years
for a spacecraft to reach proxima
centauri
so with this constraint of speed with
this speed constraint that we have right
now
it is not possible to reach our near
star system proxima centauri
within the span of one human lifetime it
would
what if one where to stand you send
human beings on on
a trip to this star system it would take
at least six thousand years
and one would need to have a number of
people
at least 100 people or more in order to
ensure that they keep producing
offspring
in the spaceship so that when the
spaceship reaches the star system there
will
still be humans there
to to visit this star system so there
have been several studies done about
this and it was found that
it was estimated that one needs at least
people at least 49 male female pairs in
such a starship
in order to ensure survival all the way
to that place to that star system
over 6 000 plus years so definitely it's
not possible within one human lifetime
uh there is currently a program called
starshot initiative if i'm not mistaken
it aims to develop a technology based on
solar sails
light sales and accelerate these
sales and small spacecraft to
about 15 to 20 the speed of light so
what
the concept is that is that
it will launch about a thousand nano
spacecraft very small spacecraft of the
weight of a few grams only
and these space shop will be powered by
solar cells by light sales
so these light cells will be impelled
by the power of lasers you can shine
lasers on these light cells
and accelerate them to about 15 to 20
the speed of light
so if one does this then these
these space probes will be able to reach
proxima centauri in about
25 to 30 years so that's what one could
possibly do in the next decade or so if
one could
develop the technologies which should
not be that difficult
so one can send robotic spacecraft
robotic space probes to proxima centauri
in the next half a century or so and get
some images back
it is possible to do that but it's not
possible to send human beings within one
human lifespan
to proxima centauri now about cryogenic
sleep
when will cryogenic sleep be possible so
let me answer first what is cryogenic
sleep
cryogenic sleep is essentially freezing
a living human being
and putting that person into a suspended
animation of sort
so the person doesn't age the person is
nearly frozen or maybe fully frozen
so that is cryogenic sleep it's about
nearly freezing the person to slow down
all the biological processes
and to bring the temperature down to
almost zero just
slightly above zero and hopefully extend
the lifespan for
several centuries and when you
reanimate the person the person comes
back to life and
it's almost like you're back to normal
that is the concept of cryogenic sleep
it's a science fiction concept
right now we are nowhere near achieving
uh
this technology uh i don't think it's
been seriously tried even right now
because there are many problems when it
comes to cryogenically
uh lowering the temperature of the human
body first of all if you lower it too
far then
ice crystals will form our body is more
than 70 water
when you freeze water ice crystals form
these ice vessels are they have very
sharp
jagged edges so at the cellular
cellular level they will basically
puncture cellular membranes
and they will reduce your internal
organs to mush
so when especially the human brain which
is full of water
so that would render the human being
unviable for reawakening it would
basically destroy the brain and destroy
the organs
and if one were to keep the temperature
above the freezing point
then we don't really know what happens i
mean some experiments were done by the
japanese in the second world war
about how long a human being can survive
such temperatures and what are the
effects but
and and that data was acquired by the
americans
and that data is still classified i'm
sure so we don't know where this
uh where where we have reached
technologically in uh trying to achieve
this
specific goal of cryogenic sleep it's
right now
completely in the realm of science
fiction we don't know what this
technology or if this technology
will ever be achievable so as of now we
can send
robotic spacecraft to proxima centauri
within
most likely the next half century and we
will be able to see what the star system
looks like it's about 4.24
light years away from us it's currently
this the closest
star system to us and there is this
planet this exoplanet that has been
discovered
it's called proxima centauri b it is an
earth-like planet it is in the habitable
zone of the star it's nearly
earth mass it's slightly larger maybe
two or three times larger
in terms of mass than the earth so one
could
one would like to send probes there and
send back images and data from there
so that could most likely be possible in
the next within the next
30 40 or 50 years so that is the stage
we are at right now right now we cannot
do interstellar travel it will be a
great thing just to send human beings to
mars and bring them back safely
that is the first step that we are
trying to achieve after sending human
beings back to the moon
so that's where we are right now it's
baby steps
right good question next question now
this is by man if technology is so
advanced
now then why are robots not used in wars
instead of humans so do you know what a
self-guided missile is
what is an anti-aircraft missile it's a
missile that autonomously targets
its target that autonomously follows
the aircraft that it's targeting and
detonates
itself near the aircraft thereby
destroying the aircraft
so it has an intelligence and a seeking
system and a guidance system of its own
that is the definition of a robot so
a an anti-aircraft missile is a robot
all these projectiles that we use in
warfare
whether they're ballistic missiles or
torpedoes
they are essentially robots
they are not very intelligent even
though now we're going to have shells
that are
that have uh that have gps embedded so
they'll be able to change the direction
in mid-flight so we are using
robotics in warfare in the recent
conflict between
armenia and azerbaijan you had these
loitering drones
that would lighten around the
battlefield for for a couple of hours
and then eventually decide autonomously
when and which when to target the enemy
and which possible
which uh vehicle or which
asset of the enemy to target so this is
intelligence and this is robotics
so we are already using robotics
and robots in warfare it's just that
they are not humanoid robots
these are robots that are not shaped
like human beings but these are robots
nonetheless
so artificial intelligence and robotics
are very much
at the core of the military of the
future
of military and the future of warfare
that's why militaries are investing so
much in it
usually when a new technology develops
anywhere
it's the military in the government that
always gets first use of it
so so ai and robotics are no different
they are being developed extensively by
various militaries
especially in the united states in china
and also in russia
so yes military i mean robotics is
already
being used in warfare and it's going to
be increasingly
um more at the center stage in warfare
so eventually you're going to have
you're gonna have uh
self driving planes planes that don't
have any human occupants they're gonna
fly on their own
they're gonna carry out their missions
on their own and they may either come
back or or
destroy themselves at the end of the
mission and the same goes for drones
drone swarms
are very much the future of of warfare
and much more so robots are already
being used in warfare and eventually i
think
most of warfare will be done by robots
so that's the answer
okay next question sr prasad asks
what jobs will be redundant because of
ais
is it applicable only to the developed
countries or even india
so the jobs that will be made redundant
because of aia
are the jobs that are that require less
skills
unskilled jobs will become redundant
very fast
for example like i said you have routine
surgeries that don't require great deal
of skill
those are now being automated by robots
and by ais
similarly various tasks such as cleaning
the streets
and other such menial tasks will
entirely be automated very soon you have
these production lines and factories
that used to have workers in the past
now you have robots there
so it is these routine tasks these low
skilled tasks
that will completely become automated
in the coming future so this is going to
impact the developing countries more
because in developing countries most
jobs are
low skilled jobs right
so now all the grocery stores stores in
india
are increasingly going out of business
especially the
small shops mom and pop shops because of
the competition from online retailers so
it's easy to
to order something from the comfort of
your phone or your computer
and it's gonna reach you in a day or two
it's gonna be delivered at your doorstep
the price is even going to be better
than what you get in your local grocery
store and you don't have to go out and
shop from different places
everything comes to your doorstep so
this is the kind of automation
and other things that are becoming
redundant
because of artificial intelligences and
big data and all that
so it's going to impact the low-income
nations
and developing countries the most it is
it's going to create this
inequality in the world the countries
that are developed
will get more powerful they'll get
richer and the countries that are
developing nations
are essentially going to become service
providers for them
so we're going to work for them online
we're going to do all the
cyber cooling work for them computing
coding programming and all that
and we will they're going to build
intellectual property
for these people for a good for for
for a wage so that's the dream of most
indians isn't it
they're gonna work for a foreign company
and we're gonna get paid in dollars
but what you're getting paid is very
little and you're building something
really valuable for them
you're building intellectual property
that they will own
so that is the future that we are
currently headed in
everything is becoming automated all
low skill and unskilled jobs are very
quickly going to become obsolete
it's going to cause great a great deal
of problems
in developing countries you're going to
have joblessness
you're going to have unrest so that is
the future that is staring us
in the face next 10 20 years is going to
be a turbulent time
unless certain steps are taken by
various governments so that is where we
are
right now it's going to affect india
definitely a lot
okay this is a couple of questions
related questions this is the last
question before i take live questions
so triptish asks will there be separate
laws for the equality and justice for
ais when they develop
emotions and shubham asks
do you think that in the future ai will
be given human rights
so ai is artificial intelligence it's a
non-human
intelligence and will it ever develop
emotions will it ever develop
consciousness we do not know
but it's a non-human intelligence it's
not a
natural intelligence it's an artificial
intelligence
it is so therefore it cannot be
classified as human beings
and therefore it cannot be given human
rights
right now we are at the situation where
we have
sentient beings on this planet animals
who have consciousness and who have
emotions who are deprived of their life
of their rights
we have millions or billions of cattle
and other animals
intelligent conscious animals with
emotions
who are enslaved who are raised for
their meat and who are slaughtered
mercilessly
and we don't give them any rights
correct they are essentially slaves they
live
a short period of time and then they are
slaughtered even when it comes to
primates the big apes the great apes
chimpanzees and gorillas and gibbons
and the orangutans and borobus
these animals are our evolutionary
cousins
they have near human levels of
intelligence compared to other animals
even dolphins are extremely intelligent
even even
elephants are very intelligent do we
give them any rights
we don't give them any rights at all
it's okay to shoot or kill such an
animal
and there's no punishment so we are not
even giving these animals
such rights so why would so it is
difficult to envisage a future in which
ais would be given rights
and we don't know if they will ever
develop emotions as we understand
emotion
we don't know if they will develop
consciousness as we understand
consciousness
so as of now i would say that in the
future it is unlikely
that you would have special laws to give
them justice and equality
and i think it's unlikely that they
would be given human rights in the
future
so great questions this is the
pre-selected questions that i'm done
with
very interesting set of questions very
interesting spectrum
of questions now i will take a few live
questions from all of you so let me take
a take a look at
live questions
okay
aliens ufos no that's not today's topic
elon musk
okay this is an interesting question
it's by shubham
since china is being choked one second
let me remove the other screen
okay so the check question is this since
china is being choked at the chip market
by the united states
and company what do you think china's
indigenous chip gamble is turning out
in the future is india focusing enough
on chips as there was news about it
so yes the united states and china are
currently engaged in a trade war the
united states is trying to deny certain
technology
technologies to china it's eventually
going to be futile china has invested in
technology
in research and development in education
in its universities
since the 1990s it has had a number of
programs
iteratively more complicated programs
more complex programs with advancing
maturity
and it has invested trillions of dollars
worth of money in these programs
so china is already almost on par with
the united states
when it comes to chip design and
artificial intelligence and quantum
computing
so china is not going to be affected
much
by the us attempts to deny it technology
and to
engage in trade warfare with it china is
advancing very fast
in some senses it may already be on the
verge of overtaking
the united states in certain aspects
of these technologies and china is has a
very mature
uh chip design and development
uh industry it's already able to produce
smartphones
and other other devices that are as good
as any device produced in the united
states or by the united states
so china is doing very well now is india
focusing in enough on ships
i think india is thinking about starting
its own chip design and chip
manufacturing industry
it won't be a designing industry it
would be a manufacturing industry
which means that we will have foreign
direct investment and foreign companies
will manufacture their chips in india
but it's going to be their proprietary
proprietary technology
it's not going to be indian technology
there will not be any technology
transfer to india
as far as i have understood the news so
india is way behind india has not
invested
in these technologies india has not
developed these technologies
indigenously
it is still i would say it's never late
india should start these things
developing chips
designing chips investing in ai quantum
computing
there is news and the government has
made some signs and some noises about
this
i don't know how far it has progressed
so that is
the current situation as we are at
okay let me try to find some other
interesting questions there are lots and
lots of questions
telekinesis well there is no evidence
that telekinesis exists
there is no scientific evidence that the
telekinesis
is possible or exists there are
apocryphal anecdotal accounts of it but
and you see that in things like star
trek etc but from
a hard scientific perspective there is
no evidence
that telekinesis is possible that's
in brief about your question
okay
population ufos again
uh let me try to find some good
questions
simulation that is not ai
okay the russians have just started mass
manufacturing war robots the war between
azerbaijan and armenia was one by the
side
with the better drones yes that's right
so like i said military technology
is increasingly dealing with robotics
you have these loitering drones that
would stay up in the air for two
three hours they would just loiter
around doing nothing
and then they would suddenly strike and
destroy tanks or vehicles of the
opponent
so yes that is the deal uh robotics are
very much part of
warfare the future of warfare is all
robotics and artificial intelligence
and enhanced soldiers with
exoskeletons and enhanced vision
and a better understanding of the
battlefield
network centric warfare understanding of
the battlefield
so that's the future and yes russia is
manufacturing
war robots and other technologies so the
future
of warfare is in all these technologies
let us see more questions
this is by shaktimaan channel what about
time travel multiverse multi-dimensions
are these possible in the future this
episode is about the future
multiverse is a hypothesis that we have
no evidence of because we cannot
see outside our universe we don't even
know
the exact limits of our universe the
observable universe is about
90 billion light years across
the actual universe may be much much
larger than that
so we have no idea of the dimensions and
extent of our own universe and we have
absolutely no idea
what's outside of our universe what's
beyond our universe so multiverse is
something that
uh it's a theory that emerges out of out
of string theory
as well as out of the many worlds
interpretation of quantum mechanics
is as of now it's just a hypothesis it
is one
especially the quantum mechanical many
worlds hypothesis
is something that is uh that many
scientists believe could be correct but
we don't have
evidence of that multiple dimensions we
again don't have evidence of it
string theory works in 10 dimensions we
have never seen these extra dimensions
we know about four dimensions length
breadth
height and time is the fourth dimension
so these are the four dimensions we can
perceive
are there more we don't know as of today
time travel
hypothetically may perhaps
be possible although
the nature of the universe may forbid
time travel so as to not uh mess up the
the causal structure of the universe so
again time travel
we don't know right now if it is
possible whether it exists whether it
will be feasible in the future
so as of now all of this is in the realm
of science fiction
okay uh next
okay this is my we have a little hope
from bengaluru regards to development of
chips it's very costly to even establish
a single plant
well that's what governments are for
they are expected to
invest in technologies
even though these investments may be
expensive
because it is these technologies that
are going to make the country
a better place and a more in a stronger
country in a more powerful country in
the future
so the government needs to make these
investments even though these
investments may be very costly
as of now it's not happening i don't
know where the future is
with respect to india one should be
hopeful and positive
and that's what i am i'm a very hopeful
and positive person so let's hope for
the best let's hope the government
does take the initiative we have the
brains in this country we have the
talent
we have the brains we have bright young
people who
would give anything to work in ai
in quantum computing and these
futuristic technologies
the government needs to empower these
people these young minds
and give them the channel the outlet
in which to channel their energies and
talents and intelligence
so i hope that happens soon
okay this is by richie brawl stars will
pilots become obsolete because of ai
taking control
of the plane eventually yes right now
we are on the verge of drivers of cars
becoming obsolete we will just be able
to sit back in the car
even sleep for a couple of hours while
the car drives us to our destination
ai at least in controlled environments
like the united states
ai is reaching is about to reach that
threshold that milestone
eventually even planes will be able to
do that we already have auto pilots in
planes
so the plane will cruise on autopilot
it's only during takeoffs and landings
and during certain periods of turbulence
etcetera that pilots actually take over
the control of the plane most of the of
the time the plane is already
flying on autopilot so eventually
why not i don't see i don't see any
reason why
ai will be soon flying planes from
start to finish it will soon happen
okay let us see another question black
hole entropy i will answer that in a
future
physics uh episode
okay benjamin matthew thank you benjamin
do you think the merge between human
consciousness and artificial
intelligence will happen
anytime soon it may be on the verge of
happening with neural link is a success
in that case you'll be able to interface
directly between
our human consciousness and with
an intelligent or artificially
intelligent computer system
so that may happen if neural link
actually works the way they
want it to work maybe in the next couple
of years maybe in the next 10 years
it is going to happen sooner or later
the effect
it will have on human consciousness is
something we don't know yet
there could be harmful effects but the
but the technology will will be brought
forth
for sure within the next decade for sure
so we are
almost there
okay next question
uh simulation optical light based
computing
that's a good question optical light
based computing
so when you talk about quantum computers
you have photons
inside them so there is there is one
form of light based computing here
it will all of these different
technologies will
soon become mainstream it may definitely
be more efficient than traditional
computing and chips
i agree with you so there's a whole
bunch there's a whole range a whole
spectrum
of technologies that are emerging right
now that in the coming decades or so
will possibly become mainstream and
optical computing
may be part of that for sure yes
brian asks what do you think about ai
being helpful to colonize
mars should we send ai robots there
first when we already sending robots to
mars these
robotic uh rovers that
have been sent to mars are robots they
have
some autonomous uh
functionality to some extent for example
there's this
robotic helicopter that's on mars right
now which does
uh operate autonomously while it's
flying because the
distance from earth to mars is is such
that we cannot control it
directly in real time so it flies
autonomously based on
the limited intelligence it has been
provided that has been built
into it so we have already sent ai
robots
to mars and even india's mangalyaan
is essentially a robot a satellite is a
robot it's a piece of machinery that
operates independently of human beings
so we are already sending
robotic probes to mars
so definitely it's helping us to gain
more
information about the planet to gain to
to
gain data and statistics about the
various conditions
on the planet which are going to be
immensely useful to us
when we actually send human beings there
so yes great question
okay one more question and we are done
for today
okay let me see something
something interesting one more question
india i think i answered that we have to
become self-reliant
okay a question about the future from
pawan
when do you think we will become a type
1 civilization
i think to become a type 1 civilization
we have to first
sort out our problems we are too busy
fighting and competing with
each other we have so much technology
we have so many resources that can solve
all our problems
all our hunger all our poverty all our
inequality
today itself and yet we are not using
all these resources in that direction we
are using these
these resources to fuel more competition
between
various countries and corporations so we
are
engaged in competition and conflict
among each other
the majority of our resources and our
energy
is being spent in this only nothing else
the technology that we have as of now it
is enough to
completely change the way we live
but it's not being used for that it's
not being used for the good of humanity
it is being used to empower governments
and to empower corporations and
individuals at the expense of
the vast majority of the seven billion
people on this planet
so we will never become a type 1
civilization as long as this condition
this this situation persists
so to become a type 1 civilization just
to clarify a kardashian type one
civilization is one that
is able to harness and control the
entire energy and resources of its home
planet
so one would be able one would need to
be able to control the weather and the
oceans and
all other sources of energy on the
planet so we are very far from being a
type 1 civilization
and the main reason the main thing
that's holding us back
is our internal conflict we human beings
are constantly fighting amongst
each other if that can be somehow
resolved then maybe we can make better
strides
in in the direction of becoming a type 1
civilization
all right guys and girls this is it
uh i'm done for the day it was a
wonderful
session many interesting topics
discussed
so i look forward to seeing you guys
tomorrow again 9pm
india time and we have another very
interesting topic coming up tomorrow
so thank you all for participating thank
you for your viewership
and i wish you a good night a good day
wherever you are
i will see you tomorrow bye